Hello, everyone. Do you like to listen to music?
Do you want to make your speakers sound better?
Or do you want to get a pair of better headphones? Well, good speakers can be pricey.
There are so many headphones in the market-- how can you choose?
How can we determine if speakers are good or bad?
Speakers are like singers. Through the
low, medium and high frequency audio signals a speaker plays,
we can tell the sound quality of speaker. What does this sound signal contain?
How should we analyze the sound played by a speaker?
Can we digitize and visualize it?
What are the criteria to determine if a speaker is good or bad?
What is sound, exactly?
No matter whether you speak, sing or play music on speakers,
sound consists of multiple frequencies
and we can analyze the distribution and energy
of each frequency using a Fourier transform.
We can pick up sounds with a microphone and then run a Fourier transform
to analyze the frequency composition of a sound clip.
For example, we can generate a composite signal consisting of 400Hz and 1000Hz
Through a Fourier transform,
we can clearly see the amplitude of both frequencies on the spectrogram.
We can also create white noise.
Here, you can see the frequency composition of white noise
So, what is white noise?
Based on the frequency energy distribution,
noises can be categorized into several types
The characteristic of white noise is that it contains all frequencies,
and the energy of each frequency is equivalent.
So we can use white noise to test if sounds are played equally by speakers.
By playing white noise, we can clearly tell from this spectrogram that
this speaker sounds bad at high and low frequency sounds.
This is called the frequency response curve of speaker.
With this, we can determine the sound characteristics of a speaker
A good speaker should be like a clear glass
that can faithfully reveal the original sound quality. So when playing white noise,
the spectrogram should show a flat line.
Is there any way we can make this frequency response curve flat?
Sure we can. We can use an equalizer to do this.
There are many types of equalizers and one we frequently use is
a parametric EQ,
also called PEQ.
PEQ features 3 parameters, including Center frequency, Q value and Gain.
First, we need to set the center frequency
to decide the frequency we want to adjust.
Second, we set Gain to cut
or boost the frequency.
The Q value determines the frequency range affected.
We can pre-process audio signals
using an equalizer to complement the sound quality of a speaker.
So, how can we optimize with an equalizer?
We can use a SigmaDSP chip to
run PEQ. On the left is a DSP demo board.
In the middle, we have a SigmaDSP ADAU1701 chip.
We can control this DSP chip using the USB to I2C converter on the right.
First, we generate an audio signal of white noise on the computer,
then send it to SigmaDSP and process with PEQ.
The signal is converted to a sound and played by the speaker.
Then we use a microphone to pick up the sound to return it to the computer
for a Fourier transform, from which we generate a spectrogram.
How can we execute PEQ on SigmaDSP?
First, we need SigmaStudio.
This is a GUI designed to process signals
The tree menu on the left provides many DSP related functions.
For example, if we want to design a PEQ,
we only need to drag in Input,
Output,
put PEQ in between,
connect with lines,
then click Compile and Download. There you go!
Click to open this PEQ and you will see a parameter setting interface.
The change of PEQ parameters will control a DSP chip in real time.
We can drag to control the center frequency and gain of PEQ
to boost or cut the energy of a specific frequency range.
For example, the frequency response curve of this speaker shows a trough on the right.
We can boost that to make it level.
We can also use several PEQs at the same time.
Each PEQ has its own center frequency, Q value and gain,
and can be used to fix a frequency response curve showing crests and troughs.
How does SigmaDSP work?
Take the most basic function, Mute, for example.
Mute simply multiplies the input signal by 0 or 1:
when multiplying by 0, the output is 0, and muted.
When we click Compile and Download,
SigmaStudio will send the program and parameters
to the DSP chip to save in different storage sections.
In DSP chip's program memory,
a piece of Mute function code looks like this.
It needs to access a value at address 0.
Location 0 refers to the address in parameter RAM.
We only need to change the value of address 0 in parameter RAM,
to control Mute using a program.
In a SigmaDSP project,
there are many other DSP functions besides Mute.
How can we know the address of each function
in parameter RAM?
The XML file provided by SigmaStudio
collects the address of all functions in parameter RAM.
How can we use Python to control a SigmaDSP chip?
We can write some cells
to support corresponding functions such as set_mute.
At the same time, we can inject the corresponding parameter address into this cell.
Then this cell will keep passing the correct parameter address
when executing set_mute function,
and eventually write the data
into the right address in DSP chip's parameter RAM
through I2C BUS.
A more complex process consists of more processing blocks.
In addition to controlling with Python,
we can also combine different control modes to write Python functions.
Eventually, we only need one-liner program to execute complex control.
So what should we do, specifically?
First, we need to locate the
SigmaStudio project XML file and
function, cell, class and definition file we write for "Factory".
Then we will generate an "IC", representing
the content of SigmaStudio project XML file.
It knows what functions are available and the corresponding addresses
in parameter RAM.
Next, Factory will create cells
for each processing block according to IC, the content of XML file,
and inject the corresponding address in parameter RAM
into cells.
In this way, we can control a DSP chip by cells.
Moreover, we can combine functions of different cells to execute a complex control procedure.
With a bit more effort,
if we add a set of TCP/IP client and server in between,
we can control remote DSP module using a wireless network.
What are the benefits of controlling a DSP module using Python and a wireless network?
First, if the module can be controlled using a wireless network, as long as a network is available,
we can control all modules, which enables easy configuration and maintenance.
Second, as we can control DSP module using Python,
we can combine many complicated functions
into one single Python function.
We can control all functions with a single-line command. Moreover, we can control
many DSP devices simultaneously through a wireless network.
Third, DSP devices
usually use microprocessors to control functions and calculate parameters,
and now we can achieve the same purpose remotely
using Python.
This can significantly simplify the internal structure of DSP devices.
Fourth, DSP devices are often equipped with many buttons and knobs.
If we can control using software through a network,
control buttons and knobs are no longer necessary.
Last, every resource should be accessed or used easily,
so the controllability of codes or
accessibility through a wireless network
ensures further development.
This is the module I used for experiments. On the left, we have a ADAU1701 chip,
a USB to I2C converter in the middle,
and a TCP/IP server on the right
The port at the bottom is for input, and the one on top is for output
With this kit, we can experiment with many applications,
such as AutoEQ.
AutoEQ optimizes the frequency response of speaker using a program.
This combination module is powered by a power bank.
The output signal is connected to a small amplifier
to generate sound through two speakers.
Here is the whole work flow:
First, make the DSP module generate a white noise signal
through the computer. After the speakers sound,
pick up sounds with the microphone and analyze with the computer,
which calculates the required PEQ parameters.
Then, configure on the DSP module through the wireless network.
The computer picks up and analyzes sounds and
sends the calculated parameters to a remote DSP module through the wireless network.
In this way, we can make speakers sound better.
In the past, the frequency response required manual adjustment.
Now, automatic optimization can be achieved remotely using a program.
First, we need to pick up sounds and analyze the spectrum.
Then we calculate the required PEQ parameters and configure the remote DSP module
through the network. In this way, we can correct the frequency response of speakers
These two graphs shows the comparison
before and after AutoEQ; the results are impressive.
During the process, to optimize PEQ parameters,
I used a Python module written by Jaakko Pasanen.
The principle is
to set the center frequency of each PEQ
according to crests and troughs in the frequency response
based on the minimum mean square error of predicted
and target response curves, optimized Q value and gain
of each PEQ by gradient descent.
Take a 2-channel speaker for example:
to get the optimal sound quality, besides adjusting the frequency response,
we also need to take care of the delay of both speakers
A signal is split into two
to sound from left and right speakers; however, the distances to the audience are different.
If we want sounds from both speakers to reach the audience at the same time,
then we need to delay the signal
of one speaker.
From the graph, we can see the red signal travels faster than the green one.
But how can we decide how much we should delay the red signal?
We can invert the red signal
When the delay is optimized,
2 signals will be offset at the utmost to reach the lowest synthesized sound pressure.
So we only need to fine-tune the delay of either signal.
The delay is optimized when we get the lowest synthesized sound pressure.
The left graph shows the relationship
of delay and synthesized sound pressure when measuring from a distance close to a pair of Bluetooth speakers
The right graph shows the result when measuring a pair of bookshelf speakers two meters away.
As the distances from the left and right speaker to the audience are different,
besides the delay, we also need to optimize the volume.
The mechanism we apply here is very simple. Make each speaker sound white noise,
adjust the volume gain of each speaker after measuring sound pressure,
and finally, make sure the volume from each speaker sounds the same to the audience.
Besides flattening the frequency response curve of a speaker,
we can design other shapes.
For example, this curve,
called the Harman Curve,
is an optimal sound frequency response that most people like in their headphones,
according to the research result of Harman International.
When designing headphones,
most manufacturers try to make the frequency response conform to Harman Curve as much as possible.
Similarly, we can implement AutoEQ
to conform the frequency response of headphones to the Harman Curve.
First, we need to find the original frequency response of the headphones.
We can measure with a device like this one.
Then, we calculate the required PEQ parameters,
or we can use the database available on the internet.
An AutoEQ almost identical to the Harman Curve
for most headphones in the market is already available,
as well as the required PEQ parameters.
With these parameters, we can adjust
the frequency response through the hardware DSP,
like a SigmaDSP chip,
or we can import the parameters to the software DSP on the computer
to correct the frequency response.
We can also
sculpt the frequency response curve into other shapes,
like the frequency response curve of other headphones.
As long as we know the frequency response of both,
we can generate the required PEQ parameters through AutoEQ
and make our headphones sound like the other one.
Here, I want to share a tool
to calculate the PEQ parameters required for frequency response conversion.
I am Wei Lin and I hope you find the content I shared today fun and interesting. Thank you for your time.